YOUMING LIU

Senior Fullstack Developer

+1 585 499 7876 • youmingliu39@gmail.com • linkedin.com/in/youming-liu421 • Ellenton, FL

Summary

Youming has over 9 years of experience in ranging from **Web** and **Mobile development** to Optimization Problems, **Machine Learning** and **Data Science** with a strong focus on **Full-Stack** web applications. He specializes in **Python**, **Typescript**, **Django**, **Node.js**, **Express**, **Nest** and **React**, **React Native**, **Vue**, **Angular** with expertise deploying to both server and serverless environments on **AWS**, **GCP** and **Azure**. He also works with relational databases and large datasets. He is the type of developer who can quickly comprehend business requirements and turn them into valuable software.

Skills

Full Stack Development · Mobile Development · Android Development · iOS Development · Devops Engineering

Javascript · Typescript · Python · PHP · Java · Golang · Ruby · HTML5 · CSS · NPM · Yarn · Vite

React · React Native · Flutter · Vue · Nuxt · Angular · Next · Gatsby · Redux · Recoil · Mobx · Zustand · Zod · Yup

SCSS · LESS · Material UI · Ant Design · Chakra UI · Styled Component · Radix UI · Shadon · Bootstrap · Tailwind CSS

Node.js · ExpressJS · NestJS · Laravel · Django · Flask · Fast API · MySQL · PostgreSQL · Redis · MongoDB · Supabase · Firebase · SQL

Github · Gitlab · Jira · Bitbucket · CI/CD Pipeline · TDD · Jest · Cypress · Mocha+Chai · Unit Testing · E2E Testing · Jenkins · NoSQL

Amazon Web Services · Google Cloud Platform · Docker · Kubernetes · Azure · Terraform · Linux · RabbitMQ · Design Patterns

Stripe · Mapbox · Google Map · Sanity · tRPC · gRPC · Zoho · Zapier

Experience

Toptal

Senior Full Stack Developer

Ellenton, FL

06/2024 - Present

- · Designed and developed a cross-browser extension with a sophisticated dashboard leveraging Plasmo, T3-stack, and PostgreSQL.
- Utilized **Shadcn UI** for intuitive UI design, **Prisma** for **ORM**, **tRPC** for seamless backend communication, and **TurboRepo** for efficient management of microservices within a **monorepo** architecture.
- Championed the use of Jest, Vitest, and Cypress for rigorous unit and end-to-end testing, ensuring high-quality code and reliable software delivery.

Fortunes Tech

Senior Full Stack Developer

Goffstown, NH 01/2024 - 07/2024

- Led a team of 7 members while performing code review, scrum planning, writing technical documentation for newcomers and managing
 the tickets on the board.
- Provide the full-stack development services utilizing the Typescript, React.js, MUI, NestJS, PostgreSQL, GraphQL, Docker, AWS and TerraForm.
- Led the UI refactoring process utilizing Material-UI, TailwindCSS and Storybook.
- Led the seamless migration from an **Express** backend with **REST API** to **Nest.js** with **GraphQL**, leveraging my advanced expertise to enhance performance, scalability, and maintainability of the application architecture.
- Successfully orchestrated the transition from **MongoDB** to **PostgreSQL**, demonstrating advanced proficiency in database management and effectively optimizing the application's data storage and retrieval capabilities.
- Designed and built robust Nest backend systems by following the Serverless Architecture based on AWS Services like AWS RDS, Lambda, API Gateway, S3, SQS, SNS, Elastic Beanstalk, CloudFormation, CloudFront.
- · Led Mobile Development including Android and iOS using React Native and Expo from scratch with engineering team.

Emergent Software

Senior Software Developer

St Paul, MN

10/2020 - 12/2023

• Assisted over 10 startup companies and projects with extensive knowledge of **Blockchain** like **Ethereum** network.

- Developed smart contracts for over 20 blockchain-related applications like Defi, NFT, P2E games and Metaverse projects.
- Created bot systems for blockchain transaction automation, including trading bots, arbitrage, and liquidations.
- Created API and WebSockets endpoints for live data feeds and direct connection to the front end.
- Developed pixel-perfect, user-friendly Web3 front end applications utilizing React, Next, Vue and Angular.js based on Figma UI/UX design
 and integrated with various Solidity smart contracts using web3.js and ethers.js.
- Optimized gas costs for a complex multi-layer smart contract replacing **solidity** code with in-line assembly.
- Helped create an upgradable contract system through a **proxy** contract system.
- · Oversaw and led the development of a decentralized and distributed team across four different time zones to build a full-stack application.

Experience

JOOR New York, NY

Full Stack Developer

01/2018 - 09/2020

- Designed and developed backend RESTful APIs with a diverse tech stack, including Node.js, Express, NestJS, PHP, Laravel, Python (Django, Flask), and databases like MongoDB, PostgreSQL, MySQL, and Redis, leveraging AWS and Firebase for scalable cloud solutions.
- Translated Figma, Adobe XD designs to pixel-perfect and fully responsive design using JavaScript, TypeScript and its libraries ReactJS, NextJS, Remix, Vue, Angular, HTML, CSS, SCSS, and LESS.
- · Migrated a healthcare web application from the LAMP stack application to a modern MERN stack app.
- · Implemented real-time communication functionalities using Web Socket and React-query.
- · Implemented Stripe API integration with payment flow, trial periods, monthly and yearly subscriptions, and withdrawals.
- Created automated testing framework in Jest, Mocha + Chai + Simon for unit testing and e2e UI testing.
- Implemented CI/CD pipelines using GitLab Actions in each step of the development cycle which improved integration and delivery towards
 agile development methodologies.

Stride New York, NY Software Engineer 06/2016 - 12/2017

- · Architected and developed robust, cross-browser-compatible health care front-end using JavaScript, TypeScript, React, and Next.js.
- · Engineered scalable Rest APIs with Express.js, ensuring high performance and reliability.
- · Implemented advanced state management and UI styling utilizing Redux, redux-saga, and TailwindCSS.
- Designed and optimized database operations with **PostgreSQL**, and enforced high code quality standards using **Jest** for comprehensive testing.
- Spearheaded the acceleration of code delivery by introducing a Continuous Integration (CI) and Continuous Delivery (CD) pipeline, dramatically improving deployment efficiency.
- · Established and maintained scalable project infrastructures on Google Cloud Platform, ensuring optimal performance and scalability.
- Ensured project stability and reduced defects by rigorously applying **TypeScript** and implementing automated testing strategies with industry standard testing frameworks.

AgileEngine Boca Raton, FL
Web Developer 05/2015 - 05/2016

- Engineered and deployed robust websites leveraging PHP MVC frameworks such as Laravel and Codelgniter to ensure maintainable and scalable architecture.
- Led the planning and execution of website development, transforming design mockups into fully functional, responsive web interfaces using Angular, HTML5, CSS, JavaScript, AJAX, and JSON.
- Implemented critical security maintenance and patching protocols on website interfaces, ensuring post-launch viability and protecting against vulnerabilities.
- Developed custom **modules** and **libraries** that are highly customizable and easily reusable, enhancing development efficiency and consistency.
- Designed and transitioned legacy websites into modern, mobile-friendly platforms, utilizing responsive design techniques to create seamless user experiences across devices.

Education

University of Pittsburgh

Master of Science - MS, Computer Science

02/2014 - 04/2015

Sun Yat-sen University

Bachelor of Science - BS, Computer Science

04/2007 - 03/2011